A Guide to the Henry Luce Foundation records, Record Group 7, Accession 2017:071 FA1547
Rockefeller Archive Center
Henry Luce Foundation records, Record Group 7, Accession 2017:071
1993-2013
Rockefeller Archive Center
Henry Luce Foundation
FA1547
7.7 Cubic Feet 18 boxes, 17 letter-size document boxes, 1 half letter-size document box
Biographical / Historical
The Henry Luce Foundation was established by Henry R. Luce in 1936. As a New York-based nonprofit organization, the Luce Foundation awards grants in American Art, Asian studies, Higher Education, Theology, and supports the Clare Boothe Luce Program for women in science, mathematics, and engineering.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Henry Luce Foundation in 2017.
Scope and Contents
The Henry Luce Foundation records (Record Group 7) contains grant files.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Arrangement
The Henry Luce Foundation records (Record Group 7) are arranged as follows:
Series 1: Project Files, 1993-2013
Art, American; Research grants -- Asia, Southeastern; Education, Higher; Environmental sciences; Theology -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; United States -- Relations -- China
- Project Files, 1993-2013; 1
  - Association of Art Museum Directors - Modern and Contemporary Asian Art Presentation, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Auburn Theological Seminary - Colleague Program, 1998-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Austin Presbyterian Theological Seminary - McCord Community Center Building, 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Azusa Pacific University - Bilingual Library in the School of Theology's Asian Center, 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Bard Graduate Center for Studies in the Decorative Arts - "Landscape Design: A Cultural and Architectural History" by Elizabeth Barlow Rogers, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Beth Israel Medical Center - Continuum Center for Health and Healing, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Biodiversity Project - Giving Voice to the Ethical Basis for Biodiversity Conservation, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Birdlife International - Threatened Birds of America, 2000-2006 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Books and Authors Vietnam, Inc. - History and Culture of Vietnam Publications, 1999-2005 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Boston University, School of Theology - Cross-Cultural Comparative Religious Ideas, 1993-2000 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Boys and Girls Harbor, Inc. - Cornell University Summer School Scholars, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Boys Club of New York - Harriman Clubhouse, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Brookings Institution - Michael Armacost Chair, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Brooks School - Henry Luce III Library, 1994-2005 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Brooklyn Museum - Reinstallation of Chinese Art, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Brown University - Enhancing the Flow of North-South Environmental Knowledge, 2001-2004 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Butler Institute of American Art - National Tour and Reinterpretation of Permanent Collection (American Collections Enhancements (ACE) Initiative), 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - California Institute of Technology - Environmental Science and Engineering at Kerckhoff Marine Lab, 2001-2006 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - California Lutheran University - "Arts in the Conejo, 1926-1989", 2000 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Cape Eleuthera Island School - Building Campaign, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Carnegie Council on Ethics and International Affairs - Comparative Study of Values in Environmental Policy Making in the United States, China, and Other Asian Countries, 1998-2006 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
  - Cathedral of Saint John the Divine - Andres Serrano: World Without End Exhibit, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Catholic Theological Union - Bernadin Center for Theology and Ministry, 1999-2003 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Center for Marine Conservation - Navassa Island Project, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Center for the Study of the Presidency - Report to the President-Elect 2000, 2000-2003 (Box 4, Folder 28-29)
  - Center of Theological Inquiry - American Conference on Faith and Order, 2000-2002 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Center of Theological Inquiry - David H.C. Read Memorial Grant, 2001-2003 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Center of Theological Inquiry - Interdisciplinary Consultations, 1996-1999 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Scope and Contents
    Faith and Responsibility in a Global Future; Theology, Science and the Future; the Scripture Project
  - Central Park Conservancy - "The Art of Central Park" 150th Anniversary Publication, 2001-2004 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Charles University, Prague - Human Rights in Central European Societies, 1997-2004 (Box 5, Folder 34-36)
  - Charles University, Prague - Human Rights Grant (Box 5, Folder 34-36)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Checkerboard Film Foundation - Brendan Gill and James Laughlin Documentary, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Cheekwood Museum of Art - American Art Collection Research, Publications, and Computerization (American Collections Enhancement (ACE) Initiative), 2000-2003 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Chesterwood (National Trust for Historic Preservation) - Daniel Chester French Permanent Exhibit, 1997-2003 (Box 5, Folder 39-40)
  - Chicago Theological Seminary - "Partners in Theological Education" Needs Assessment Study, 1998-2005 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Childhelp USA - Childhelp Village South, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - China Institute in America - Resonance of Qin in Far Eastern Art, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Harvard Art Museums - Fogg Art Museum American Art Catalog, 2001-2008 (Box 6, Folder 44-45)
  - High Museum of Art - "The First Emperor: China's Terracotta Army" Exhibition, 2007-2011 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Huazhong Normal University - Research Library on the History of Christianity in China, 2003-2011 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Indiana University - Western Medicine in China, 2010-2011 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - International Center - Asian Communities in New York, 2002-2011 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Japan Center for International Exchange - Role of Philanthropy in Post-War Japan Relations, 2003-2006 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Living Pulpit - Endowmwnet Campaign Honoring David H.C. Read, 2001-2003 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Long Island University - Textbook on the Modern History of Southeast Asia, 2000-2011 (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Madison Square Park Conservancy - Public Art Program, 2006-2008 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Maryknoll Mission Association for the Faithful - Muslim-Christian Project in Southeast Asia and Sub-Sahara Africa, 2004-2006 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Metro International - Global Classroom, 2001-2004 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Missouri Botanical Garden - Botanical Training in Vietnam, 2000-2005 (Box 7, Folder 56-57)
  - Montgomery Museum of Fine Arts - American Paintings Collection, 2005-2006 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Museum of Arts and Sciences - American Art Collection (American Collections Enhancement (ACE) Initiative), 2000-2004 (Box 8, Folder 59-60)
  - Museum of Contemporary Art, Chicago - "Lee Bontecou: A Retrospective of Sculpture and Drawing, 1958-2004" Exhibition and Catalog, 2001-2005 (Box 8, Folder 61-62)
  - Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles - "Toward a Minimalist Future: Art as Object, 1958-1968" Exhibition and Catalog, 1999-2004 (Box 9, Folder 63-64)
  - Museum of Modern Art - "Plane Image: A Brice Marden Retrospective" Exhibition and Catalog, 2005-2007 (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Museum of Modern Art - "Richard Serra Sculpture: 40 Years" Exhibition and Catalog, 2006-2007 (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Museum of Scotland - Capital Campaign, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - National Academy of Design - Gallery Wall Renovation, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - National Academy of Design - Stuart Davis Exhibition, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 69)
  - National Arts Journalism Program - "The Artist in the Media" Research Project, 2005-2007 (Box 9, Folder 70)
  - National Audubon Society - New York State Important Bird Area Program, 2001-2005 (Box 9, Folder 71)
  - National Bureau of Asian Research - Politics of State Owned Enterprises Reform and China's Economic Future, 1999-2002 (Box 9, Folder 72)
  - National Center for Leadership - National Fellows Program in Leadership, 1997-2004 (Box 10, Folder 73)
  - National Committee on American Foreign Policy - Multilateral Conference on the North Korean Nuclear Issue, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 74)
  - National Committee on United States-China Relations - Airlie House Conference, 1999-2000 (Box 10, Folder 75)
  - National Gallery of Art - "Drawing on America's Past: Folk Art, Modernism, and the Index of American Design" Exhibition and Catalog, 2001-2004 (Box 10, Folder 76)
  - National Gallery of Art - "Sculpture of Angkor and Ancient Cambodia" Exhibition, 1995-2000 (Box 10, Folder 77-78)
  - National Humanities Center - Interdisciplinary Fellowship Program, 1995-1999 (Box 10, Folder 79)
  - National Institute of Social Sciences - The Moral Authority of Government, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 80)
  - National Museum of American Art - Reframing of Paintings, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 81)
  - National Religious Partnership for the Environment - Earth's Climate Embraces Us All Program, 2006-2008 (Box 11, Folder 82)
  - National Schools Committee of Economic Education - "I, Pencil" Essay Adaptation, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 83)
  - National Schools Committee of Economic Education - The Economics Game, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 84)
  - National Trust for Historic Preservation - Historic Artists' Homes and Studios Program, 1999-2003 (Box 11, Folder 85-87)
  - National Trust for Historic Preservation - Historic Artists' Homes and Studios Program (Renewal), 2002-2008 (Box 12, Folder 88-89)
  - National Trust for Historic Preservation - Hurricane Katrina Recovery Fund, 2005-2009 (Box 12, Folder 90)
  - Natural Resources Defense Council - Green Communities Initiative, 2005-2008 (Box 12, Folder 91)
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller Institute of Government (State University of New York) - Center for Effective Public Higher Education, 1996-1998 (Box 12, Folder 92)
  - New Museum of Contemporary Art - Marcia Tucker Hall, 2004-2008 (Box 13, Folder 93-95)
  - New School of Social Research - Impact of Immigration on New York City, 1996-2001 (Box 13, Folder 96-97)
  - New-York Historical Society - Curatorial Fellowship for the Painting and Sculpture Collection, 2001-2006 (Box 13, Folder 98)
  - New-York Historical Society - "New York's Finest: The History of the New York City Police Department" Exhibition, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 99)
  - New York Landmarks Conservancy - St. Michael's 1895 Tiffany Windows, 2001-2003 (Box 14, Folder 100)
  - New York Public Library - Chinese Vernacular Collection, 1999-2003 (Box 14, Folder 101)
  - New York Regional Association of Grantmakers (Philanthropy New York) - New York City Youth Funders Program Activities, 2005 (Box 14, Folder 102)
  - New York State Archives Partnership Trust - Research Fellows Program, 1996-1999 (Box 14, Folder 103)
  - New York Studio School of Drawing, Painting, and Sculpture - Studio Instruction, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 104)
  - Newark Museum - American Art Collection Scholarship, Documentation, and Programs, 2002-2008 (Box 14, Folder 105)
  - Northern Baptist Theological Seminary - Library Automation, 1996-2001 (Box 14, Folder 106)
  - Northern Illinois University - First International Lao Studies Conference, 2005-2011 (Box 14, Folder 107)
  - Georgia O'Keeffe Museum - William I. Homer Archive, 2004-2008 (Box 15, Folder 108)
  - Opera Music Theater International - The Greening of a Cultural Wasteland, 1999 (Box 15, Folder 109)
  - Orange County Museum of Art - California Artists Archive, 2005-2007 (Box 15, Folder 110)
  - Our Lady of Grace Church - Renovation of Sanctuary and Rectory, 2001 (Box 15, Folder 111)
  - Oxford University Press - Barabara Novak Trilogy, 2005-2007 (Box 15, Folder 112)
  - Pacific Institute - Water and Sustainability Program, 2000-2005 (Box 15, Folder 113)
  - Parent Project for Muscular Dystrophy Research - Kids for Kids Project, 2001 (Box 15, Folder 114)
  - Partners for Sacred Places - Sacred Places Make Good Community, 1998-2005 (Box 15, Folder 115-116)
    Program for congregations in older and historic buildings.
  - Plymouth Congregational Church - Continuing Education for Clergy Pilot Program, 1997-2000 (Box 15, Folder 117)
  - Police Athletic League - Educational Resource Center at the Central Harlem Center, 1999-2003 (Box 16, Folder 118)
  - Springfield Museums - Art Preparator and Part-Time Curatorial Assistant (American Art Renewal Fund), 2011-2013 (Box 16, Folder 119)
  - Taft Museum of Art - "Hiram Powers: Genius in Marble" Exhibition and Catalog, 2006-2009 (Box 16, Folder 120)
  - Temple University - Vietnam Studies Center, 2004-2012 (Box 16, Folder 121-123)
  - Toledo Museum of Art - American Art Collection, 2009-2013 (Box 17, Folder 124)
  - United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia - Luce Buildings, 2006-2009 (Box 17, Folder 125)
  - University of California, Berkeley - Berkeley China Initiative, 2006-2008 (Box 17, Folder 126)
  - University California, San Diego - American Studies Seminar for Asian Professionals (PacRim Summer Seminar), 2004-2013 (Box 17, Folder 127)
  - University of San Francisco - History of Christianity in China, 2008-2013 (Box 18, Folder 128)
  - University of Texas, Austin - A Portfolio Program in Sustainable Design and Development, 2005-2013 (Box 18, Folder 129-130)